part 1 chapter 4.
With the deep, unconscious sigh which not even the nearness of the telescreen
could prevent him from uttering when his day's work started, Winston pulled the
speak right towards him, blew the dust from its mouthpiece and put on his spectacles.
Then he unrolled and clipped together four small cylinders of paper which had
already flopped out of the pneumatic tube on the right hand side of his desk.
In the walls of the cubicle there were three orifices.
To the right of the speak right a small pneumatic tube for written messages; to
the left, a larger one for newspapers; and in the sidewall within easy reach of
Winston's arm, a large oblong slit protected by a wire grating.
This last was for the disposal of waste paper.
Similar slits existed in thousands or tens of thousands throughout the
building, not only in every room but at short intervals in every corridor.
For some reason they were nicknamed memory holes.
When one knew that any document was due for destruction, or even when one saw a
scrap of waste paper lying about, it was an automatic action to lift the flap of
the nearest memory hole and drop it in whereuponnet would be whirled away on a
current of warm air to the enormous furnaces which were hidden somewhere in
the recesses of the building.
Winston examined the four slips of paper which he had unrolled. Each contained a
message of only one or two lines, in the abbreviated jargon— —not actually news
speak but consisting largely of Newspeak words— —which was used in the Ministry for
internal purposes.
They ran: times 17 384 bb speech male reported africa rectify
times 19 1283 forecasts 3yp 4th quarter 83 misprints verify current issue
times 14 to 84 mini plenty malquoted chocolate rectify times 3 1283 reporting bb day order
double plus ungood riffs on Persons rewrite full wise up sub anti-filing
With a faint feeling of satisfaction Winston laid the fourth message aside.
It was an intricate and responsible job and had better be dealt with last.
The other three were routine matters, though the second one would probably
mean some tedious waiting through lists of figures.
Winston dialed back numbers' on the telescreen and called for the
appropriate issues of the Times, which slid out of the pneumatic tube after
only a few minutes' delay.
The messages he had received referred to articles or news items which for one
reason or another it was thought necessary to alter, or, as the official
phrase had it, to rectify.
For example, it appeared from the Times of the 17th of March that Big Brother, in
his speech of the previous day, had predicted that the South Indian front
would remain quiet but that the Eurasian offensive would shortly be launched in North Africa.
As it happened the Eurasian Higher Command had launched its offensive in
South India and left North Africa alone.
It was therefore necessary to rewrite a paragraph of Big Brother's speech, in
such a way as to make him predict the thing that had actually happened.
Or again, the Times of the 19th of December had published the official
forecasts of the output of various classes of consumption goods in the
fourth quarter of 1983,. which was also the sixth quarter of the Ninth Three-Year Plan.
Today's issue contained a statement of the actual output, from which it appeared
that the forecasts were in every instance grossly wrong.
Winston's job was to rectify the original figures by making them agree with the later ones.
As for the third message, it referred to a very simple error which could be set
right in a couple of minutes a shorter time ago as February, the
Ministry of Plenty had issued a promise (a 'categorical pledge with the official
words) that there would be no reduction of the chocolate ration during 1984..
Actually, as Winston was aware, the chocolate ration was to be reduced from
30 grams to 20 at the end of the present week.
All that was needed was to substitute for the original promise a warning that
it would probably be necessary to reduce the ration at some time in April
foreign As soon as Winston had dealt with each of the messages, he clipped his
speak written corrections to the appropriate copy of the Times and pushed
them into the pneumatic tube.
Then, with a movement which was nearly as possible unconscious, he crumpled up the
original message and any notes that he himself had made, and dropped them into
the memory hole to be devoured by the flames.
What happened in the unseen labyrinth to which the pneumatic tubes led, he did not
know in detail, but he did know in general terms.
As soon as all the corrections which happened to be necessary in any
particular number of the Times had been assembled and collated, that number would
be reprinted, the original copy destroyed, and the corrected copy placed on the
files in its stead.
This process of continuous alteration was applied not only to newspapers, but
to books, periodicals, pamphlets, posters, leaflets, films, soundtracks, cartoons,
photographs— —to every kind of literature or documentation which might conceivably
hold any political or ideological significance.
Day by day and almost minute by minute the past was brought up to date.
In this way every prediction made by the Party could be shown by documentary
evidence to have been correct; nor was any item of news, or any expression of
opinion, which conflicted with the needs of the moment, ever allowed to remain on record.
All history was a palimpsest, scraped clean and re-inscribed exactly as often as was necessary.
In no case would it have been possible, once the deed was done, to prove that any
falsification had taken place.
The largest section of the Records Department, far larger than the one on
which Winston worked, consisted simply of persons whose duty it was to track down
and collect all copies of books, newspapers and other documents which had
been superseded and were due for destruction.
A number of the Times which might, because of changes in political
alignment, or mistaken prophecies uttered by Big Brother, have been rewritten a
dozen times still stood on the files bearing its original date, and no other
copy existed to contradict it.
Books, also, were recalled and Rewritten again and again, and were invariably
reissued without any admission that any alteration had been made.
Even the written instructions which Winston received, and which he invariably
got rid of as soon as he had dealt with them, never stated or implied that an act
of forgery was to be committed: always the reference was to slips, errors,
misprints or misquotations which it was necessary to put right in the interests of accuracy.
But actually, he thought as he readjusted the Ministry of Plenty's figures, it was
not even forgery. It was merely the substitution of one piece of nonsense for another.
Most of the material that you were dealing with had no connection with
anything in the real world, not even the kind of connection that is contained in a direct lie.
Statistics were just as much a fantasy in their original version as in their rectified version.
A great deal of the time you were expected to make them up out of your head.
For example, the Ministry of Plenty's forecast had estimated the output of
boots for the quarter at 145 million pairs.
The actual output was given as 62 millions.
Winston, however, in rewriting the forecast, marked the figure down to 57
millions, so as to allow for the usual claim that the quota had been over fulfilled
In any case 62 millions was no nearer the truth than 57 millions more than 145
millions. Very likely no boots had been produced at all
likely as still, nobody knew how many had been produced, much less cared.
All one knew was that every quarter astronomical numbers of boots were
produced on paper, while perhaps half the population of Oceania went barefoot.
And so it was with every class of recorded fact, great or small.
Everything faded away into a shadow World in which, finally, even the date of
the year had become uncertain.
Winston glanced across the hall. In the corresponding cubicle on the other side
a small precise looking dark chinned man named Tillotson was working steadily
away, with a folded newspaper on his knee and his mouth very close to the
mouthpiece of the speak right He had the air of trying to keep what he
was saying a secret between himself and the telescreen.
He looked up, and his spectacles started a hostile flash in Winston's direction.
Winston hardly knew Tillerson and had no idea what work he was employed on.
People in the Records Department did not readily talk about their jobs.
In the long, windowless hall, with its double row of cubicles and its endless
rustle of papers and hum of voices murmuring into speak rights there were
quite a dozen people whom Winston did not even know by name, though he daily
saw them hurrying to and fro in the corridors or gesticulating in the Two Minutes Hate.
He knew that in the cubicle next to him the little woman with sandy hair toiled
day in, day out, simply it's tracking down into deleting from the press the names
of people who had been vaporized and were therefore considered never to have existed.
There was a certain fitness in this, since her own husband had been vaporized
a couple of years earlier a few cubicles away a mild, ineffectual,
dreamy creature named appleforth with very hairy ears and a surprising talent
for juggling with rhymes and meters was engaged in producing garbled diversions
definitive texts, they were called— —of poems which had become ideologically
offensive but which for one reason or another were to be retained in the anthologies.
And this hall, with its 50 workers or thereabouts, was only one subsection a
single cell, as it were, in the huge complexity of the Records Department.
Beyond, above, below where other swarms of workers engaged in an unimaginable multitude of jobs.
There was a huge printing shops with their sub-editors, their typography
experts and their elaborately equipped studios for the faking of photographs.
There was the teller programs section with its engineers, its producers and its
teams of actors specially chosen for their skill in imitating voices.
There were the armies of reference clerks whose job was simply to draw up
lists of books and periodicals which were due for recall.
There were the vast repositories where the corrected documents were stored, and
the hidden furnaces where the original copies were destroyed.
And somewhere or other, quite anonymous, there were the directing brains who
coordinated the whole effort and laid down the lines of policy which made it
necessary that this fragment of the past should be preserved, that one falsified,
and the other rubbed out of existence.
And the Records Department, after all, was itself only a single branch of the
Ministry of Truth, whose primary job was not to reconstruct the past but to
supply the citizens of Oceania with newspapers, films, textbooks, telescreen
programs plays, novels— with every conceivable kind of information,
instruction or entertainment, from a statue to a slogan, from a lyric poem to
a biological treatise, and from a child's spelling book to a Newspeak dictionary.
And the Ministry had not only to supply the multifarious needs of the Party, but
also to repeat the whole operation at a lower level for the benefit of the proletariat.
There was a whole chain of separate departments dealing with proletarian
literature, music, drama and entertainment generally.
Here were produced rubbish newspapers containing almost nothing except sport,
crime and astrology, sensational five cent novelets films oozing with sex, and
sentimental songs which were composed entirely by mechanical means on a
special kind of kaleidoscope known as a versificator.
There was even a whole subsection porno second was called in Newspeak— —engaged in
producing the lowest kind of pornography, which was sent out in sealed packets and
which no Party member, other than those who worked on it, was permitted to look at.
Three messages had slid out of the pneumatic tube while Winston was working;
but they were simple matters, and he had disposed of them before the Two Minutes
Hate interrupted him.
When the Hate was over he returned to his cubicle, took the Newspeak dictionary
from the shelf, pushed the speak writer to one side, cleaned his spectacles and
settled down to his main job of the morning.
Winston's greatest pleasure in life was in his work. Most of it was a tedious
routine, but included in it there were also jobs so difficult and intricate
that you could lose yourself in them as in the depths of a mathematical problem—
—delicate pieces of forgery in which you had nothing to guide you except your
knowledge of the principles of insock and your estimate of what the Party wanted you to say.
Winston was good at this kind of thing.
On occasion he had even been entrusted with the rectification of the Times
leading articles, which were written entirely in Newspeak. He unrolled the
message that he had set aside earlier. It ran: times 3 1283 reporting bb day order
double plus ungood riffs unpersons rewrite full wise up sub anti-filing
In Old speak or Standard English) this might be rendered:
The reporting of Big Brother's Order for the Day in the Times of December the 3rd
1983 is extremely unsatisfactory and makes references to non-existent persons
rewrite it in full and submit your draft to higher authority before filing.
Winston read through the offending article.
Big Brother's Order for the Day, it seemed, had been chiefly devoted to
praising the work of an organization known as FFCC, which supplied cigarettes
and other comforts to the sailors in the Floating Fortresses.
A certain Comrade Withers, a prominent member of the Inner Party, had been
singled out for special mention and awarded a decoration, the Order of
Conspicuous Merit, Second Class.
Three months later FFCC had suddenly been dissolved with no reasons given.
One could assume that Withers and his associates were now in disgrace, but
there had been no report of the matter in the press or on the telescreen.
That was to be expected, since it was unusual for political offenders to be
put on trial or even publicly denounced.
The great purges involving thousands of people, with public trials of traitors
and thought criminals who made abject confession of their crimes and were
afterwards executed with special showpieces not occurring often than once in a couple of years.
More commonly, people who had incurred the displeasure of the Party simply
disappeared and were never heard of again.
One never had the smallest clue as to what had happened to them.
In some cases they might not even be dead.
Perhaps 30 people personally known to Winston, not counting his parents, had
disappeared at one time or another.
Winston stroked his nose gently with a paperclip In the cubicle across the way Comrade
Tillerson was still crouching secretively over his speak right
He raised his head for a moment: again the hostile spectacle Flash
Winston wondered whether Comrade Tillerson was engaged on the same job as
himself. It was perfectly possible.
So tricky a piece of work would never be entrusted to a single person: on the
other hand, to turn it over to a committee would be to admit openly that
an act of fabrication was taking place.
Very likely as many as a dozen people were now working away on rival versions
of what Big Brother had actually said.
And presently some master brain in the Inner Party would select this version or
that, would re-edit it and set in motion the complex processes of
cross-referencing that would be required, and then the chosen lie would pass into
the permanent records and become truth.
Winston did not know why Withers had been disgressed Perhaps it was for
corruption or incompetence.
Perhaps Big Brother was merely getting rid of a too popular subordinate.
Perhaps Withers or someone close to him had been suspected of heretical tendencies.
Or perhaps— —what was likeliest of all— —the thing had simply happened because purges
and vaporizations were a necessary part of the mechanics of government.
The only real clue lay in the woods Rifts unpersons', which indicated that
Withers was already dead.
You could not invariably assume this to be the case when people were arrested.
Sometimes they were released and allowed to remain at liberty for as much as a
year or two years before being executed.
Very occasionally some person whom you had believed did long since would make a
ghostly reappearance at some public trial where he would implicate hundreds
of others by his testimony before vanishing, this time forever
with us however, was already an unperson.
He did not exist: he had never existed.
Winston decided that it would not be enough simply to reverse the tendency of
Big Brother's speech. It was better to make it deal with something totally
unconnected with its original subject.
He might turn the speech into the usual denunciation of traitors and thought
criminals but that was a little too obvious; while to invent a victory at the
front, or some triumph of verbal production in the Ninth Three-Year Plan,
might complicate the records too much.
What was needed was a piece of pure fantasy.
Suddenly they sprang into his mind ready-made as it were, the image of a
certain Comrade Ogilby who had recently died in battle, in heroic circumstances.
There were occasions when Big Brother devoted his Order for the Day to
commemorating some humble Rank and file Party member whose life and death he
held up as an example worthy to be followed.
Today he should commemorate Comrade Ogilvy. It was true that there was no
such person as Comrade Ogilvy a few lines of print and a couple of faked
photographs would soon bring him into existence.
Winston thought for a moment, then pulls the speak right towards him and began
dictating in Big Brother's familiar style: a style at once military and
pedantic, and, because of a trick of asking questions and then promptly answering them
('What lessons do we learn from this fact, comrades? The lesson— —which is also one of
the fundamental principles of insock that,' etc. etc.), easy to imitate.
At the age of three Comrade Ogilvy had refused all toys except a drum, a
submachine gun and a model helicopter six— —a year early, by a special relaxation
of the rules— —he had joined the Spies; at
nine he had been a troop leader. At 11 he had denounced his uncle to the Thought
Police after overhearing a conversation which appeared to him to have criminal tendencies.
At 17 he had been a district organizer of the Junior Anti-Sex League
19 he had designed a hand grenade which had been adopted by the Ministry of
Peace and which, at its first trial, had killed 31 Eurasian prisoners in one burst.
At 23 he had perished in action.
Pursued by enemy jet planes while flying over the Indian Ocean with important
dispatches he had weighted his body with his machine gun and leapt out of the
helicopter into deep water dispatches and all— —an Ender said Big Brother, which
it was impossible to contemplate without feelings of envy.
Big Brother added a few remarks on the purity and single-mindedness of Comrade Ogilvy's life.
He was a total abstainer and a non-smoker, had no recreations except a
daily hour in the gymnasium, and had taken a vow of celibacy, believing
marriage and the care of a family to be incompatible with the 24-hour a Day devotion to duty.
He had no subjects of conversation except the principles of exoc and no aim
in life except the defeat of the Eurasian enemy and the hunting down of
spies, saboteurs thought criminals and traitors generally.
Winston debated with himself whether to award Comrade Ogle via the Order of
Conspicuous Merit: in the end he decided against it because of the unnecessary
cross-referencing that it would entail.
Once again he glanced at his rival in the opposite cubicle.
Something seemed to tell him with certainty that Tillotson was busy on the same job as himself.
There was no way of knowing whose job would finally be adopted, but he felt a
profound conviction that it would be his own.
Comrade Ogilvy, unimagined an hour ago, was now a fact.
It struck him as curious that you could create dead men but not living ones.
Comrade Ogilvy, who had never existed in the present, now existed in the past, and
when once the act of forgery was forgotten, he would exist just as
authentically, and upon the same evidence, as Charlotte or Julius Caesar